IN CONTROL
INTERFACING PROJECTS FOR BEGINNERS
BY DARREN GRANT

If you want a change from playing games or browsing the internet, what else is there that you can do with a computer? What I would like to share with you is the tremendous fascination of using a computer for control. You can get the computer to switch things on and off, respond to events and take a variety of measurements. This is known as ‘interfacing’.

If you feel your knowledge of electronics is rather limited, don’t despair in this series we are not assuming that you have more than a basic understanding of electronics. The aim is to explain the basics and provide details of relatively simple hardware and basic software to get started.

The Raspberry Pi provides an ideal way to begin experimenting. Not only does the low cost of the Pi mean that there is no need to worry about damage to an expensive computer, it also comes ready equipped with the connections to get started right away.

As you will have no doubt probably figured out already computers are all about In’s and Out’s. Input something on the keyboard or click with a mouse and get something out on the screen or sound out of the speakers. Interfacing is simply finding other ways of getting information in and out of the computer.

The first thing to understand is that the basic building blocks of a computer are made up of millions of switches called transistors. Computers see everything as either on or off so when you click the mouse button the switch is on and when you let go it is off. The computer has no idea how hard the button has been pressed. This is known as a digital binary system, when a switch is on it is represented by a ‘1’ (one) and when it is off a ‘0’ (zero). Signals that are variable such as measuring temperature are called analogue, as they are more complicated than just a simple on or off state extra equipment is needed so the computer can read them.

For now we will stick with a simple digital interface. The Raspberry Pi has a set of connections called the GPIO (General Purpose Input Output) port. GENERAL PURPOSE means that they have not been assigned a specific purpose, unlike for example the speaker connection that has a well defined purpose. The connections on the GPIO port can be used for whatever purpose you like. Each connection can be used as an INPUT where the computer is waiting for an event to happen such as a switch being pressed or an OUTPUT where the computer is sending a signal out for example to switch a light or buzzer on and off.

The GPIO ports on the raspberry Pi are low powered so an expansion board is recommended to provide higher powered signals that can be used for controlling things like lamps, buzzers and motors. A GPIO expansion board also provides some protection to the Raspberry Pi just in case something is connected incorrectly.

Don’t worry if you don’t have a GPIO expansion board at this stage and you are raring to get going with your first experiment. Providing you take care we can start with a simple circuit using a switch and a LED (Light Emitting Diode). ►

IMPORTANT
Before connecting anything to the Raspberry Pi please be aware that incorrect connections could cause damage. Please take care.

Switch Types

An electrical switch is used to make or break an electrical circuit. Switches are binary devices: they are either completely on (closed) or completely off (open) making an ideal starting point for our interfacing experiments. There are many different types of switches, the simplest type being one where two electrical conductors are brought in contact with each other by manually moving a mechanism.

There are essentially two common types of switch, latching switches and momentary types. A latching switch stays open or closed when activated, for example a light switch; when you switch the light on or off the switch stays in the same position until you switch it again. A momentary switch on the other hand will only operate while pressure is being applied and will return to its previous state when released. Momentary switches can be found on a game controller where the control only responds while the button is being pressed. A momentary switch wouldn’t make a very good light switch as you wouldn’t want to have to keep the button pressed to keep the light on. The electrical symbol for a simple momentary push switch is like this.

We will use a small momentary push button switch for this experiment, known as a normally open tactile switch.

LEDs

LEDs (Light Emitting Diodes) can be found everywhere, commonly used as indicator lights on most electronic equipment such as the standby light on your TV. Due to the small amount of power needed to make a LED light up, we can safely use them in our experiment without damaging the Raspberry Pi.

The symbol for a LED looks like this.

To save soldering wires together a breadboard and a selection of jumper wires is highly recommended, it makes connecting things together very easy and flexible. The grid reference numbers are laid out on a small 270 point Tandy breadboard. If you have a bigger board that will work just as well but the reference numbers may not match so will need to be modified if your board has a slightly different grid layout.

Place the components on the breadboard using the illustration as a guide. If your tactile switch has inward pointing legs like the one shown in the photo on the top left, use a small pair of pliers to straighten them. The switch needs to be inserted into the breadboard so that the legs are on the left and right edges. It is also important that the LED is connected the correct way round, the positive terminal called the anode is the longer leg and should be connected to point C4. Once all the components are in place connect the circuit to the Raspberry Pi using 3 female to male jumper wires, taking extra care to connect the correct terminals. The Raspberry Pi GPIO pins in the illustration are shown when looking at the board with the GPIO header in the top left corner, as shown in the photo in the Pi Dissection article on page 16.

Having connected everything together, power up the Raspberry Pi and try pressing the button, the LED should light up. If it doesn’t work check that all the components and wires are connected correctly, paying particular attention to the LED. If the LED stays on without pressing the button then the switch is probably connected incorrectly and will need to be turned 90°. ►

Circuit Description

Because the Raspberry Pi GPIO port is not protected
with a buffer, we have included a 1KΩ (Ohm)
resistor (R2) between the switch and the GPIO pin
as a precaution to prevent damage if the GPIO port
is accidentally set as an output. Our tactile switch is
connected to the 0V or ground line so that when it is
pressed the circuit is completed between the GPIO
pin and zero Volts.

The LED along with a 470Ω current limiting resistor
(R1) is connected to the 3.3V positive rail. Pressing
the switch completes the circuit between the LED
and 0V causing it to light up, this provides a visual
indication when the switch is pressed. Finally we
have a 10KΩ pull-up resistor (R3).

Digital Logic States

As mentioned earlier computers see the world as
a series of zeros and ones. The Raspberry Pi uses
3.3V CMOS logic meaning that a binary 1 is created
by applying a voltage of 3.3V to an input. When the
voltage is present it is referred to as a logic HIGH
state. Alternatively when the GPIO pin is connected
to 0V a binary 0 or logic LOW state is created. In
our switch example pressing the switch creates a
LOW state by connecting the IO port to 0V. ►

Shopping List
COMPONENTS
1x 3mm Red LED (standard brightness)
1x 470Ω Resistor
1x 1kΩ Resistor
1x 10kΩ Resistor
1x Miniature PCB Tactile Switch
ACCESSORIES
1x Breadboard
3x Male-female jumper wires
1x Selection of short jumper wires
TOOLS
If you don’t have them already then
a set of small long nosed pliers for
bending component leads and wire
cutters will make construction easier.

Digital logic in fact has three possible states known as Tri-State logic. We have already discussed HIGH (+3.3V) and LOW (0V) states but we also have a third state that is called FLOATING. Basically floating means the state is not clearly defined, attempting to determine the status of a connection that is floating may result in unpredictable results. You might be thinking that if the pin is not connected to a voltage it must be low: the problem is we can not guarantee that we will get a reliable LOW signal by simply relying on the absence of a voltage on the pin.

To illustrate the problem, imagine that we hold a piece of ribbon between two gate posts, the two gate posts would be connected by the ribbon. Now if we let one end of the ribbon go and allow it to fall to the ground the two posts are no longer connected. But what happens when the wind blows? The ribbon will flap around where sometimes it will be in contact with the ground and other times it will touch or even become entangled with the other post. To prevent the ribbon moving in the wind we would tie it either to the ground or the post so it wouldn’t move unless we wanted it to. We need to do the same thing with a logic circuit, to avoid unpredictable behaviour we tie the connection to either 3.3V or 0V using what is known as a pull-up or pull-down resistor that effectively creates a default state. In this experiment we have used a pull-up resistor so the IO port will always be connected to +3.3V making it the default state. In our example when reading the state of the IO pin it will always be high until we press the switch that will change it to low.

Software

Having completed the circuit construction we now have to get the Raspberry Pi to recognise the switch. To do this we need to create a software program that will instruct the Pi to monitor the switch status.

We will be using the Python programming language to write our program. It is assumed that you are using the standard Debian “squeeze” operating system from the Raspberry Pi website. If you have not used Python before take a look at the guide to editing and running Python programs on page 24.

The first thing we need to do is install a Python package that adds the capability to Python to control the GPIO pins on the Raspberry Pi. Download the Python package from
http://pypi.python.org/pypi/RPi.GPIO the latest version at the time of writing this article is RPi.GPIO-0.2.0. If the file version downloaded is different then the instructions below will need to be modified to use the version number you have downloaded.

We will use the terminal to install the package, to open the terminal go to the main menu, select accessories and click on LXTerminal which will open a new window with a command prompt. The file is compressed and archived, to install it we will need to decompress and unarchive it by typing the following commands.

gunzip RPi.GPIO-0.2.0.tar.gz
tar -xvf RPi.GPIO-0.2.0.tar

We now have a new directory called RPi.GPIO-0.2.0 that we need to go into and run the setup script, type the following commands to complete the installation.

cd RPi.GPIO-0.2.0
sudo python setup.py install

You may be asked for your password when running the install script. If you have not changed the password the default is ‘raspberry’.
Now that the package installation is complete we can write a program to monitor the switch and write something to the screen each time it is pressed. Before we start programming: at the command prompt type the following command to return to the home directory. ►

cd ..

Python Program

Create a new text file named mybutton.py and
enter the following program.

#!/usr/bin/python
import time
import RPi.GPIO as GPIO
GPIO.setup(11, GPIO.IN)
while True:
mybutton = GPIO.input(11)
if mybutton == False:
print "giggle"
time.sleep(.2)

Program Description

We start by including the time and RPi.GPIO
packages in our program so we can make use
of their functions by using import.

Next we configure GPIO pin 11 on the raspberry
Pi as an input so it can detect the switch.

By using ‘while True’ we create a never ending
loop so that everything below this will be
repeated until we choose to stop it.

Our program keeps checking the status of pin
11 that will always be True (High) while the
button is not being pressed. As soon as the
button is pressed the GPIO pin goes low and
our result will be False: at which point we print
out the word “giggle” on the screen. Because
the program runs much quicker than we can
press and release the button we add a small
0.2 second delay before checking the button
status again so that the screen does not fill up
with giggles.

To start the program type the following command
into the terminal window.

sudo python mybutton.py

When you have had enough giggles press the
Control+C keys to stop
the program.

Counting

Try the following program to count the number
of times the button is pressed.

#!/usr/bin/python
import time
import RPi.GPIO as GPIO
GPIO.setup(11, GPIO.IN)
count = 0
while True:
mybutton = GPIO.input(11)
if mybutton == False:
count = count+1
print "count", count
time.sleep(.2)

Conclusion

We have covered how to make the computer
respond to a switch circuit and written a simple
program. Now that you have mastered
the basics how about you try and improve the
program. For example make a timer program
that will start and stop counting when pressing
the button. Why not send in your programs
and questions to in.control@themagpi.com or
get involved on the official Raspberry Pi forum,
maybe we can include some of them in the
next instalment. ●

This article is sponsored by Tandy.
Look out for our new web site coming soon: where you will
find all the components you need for your Raspberry Pi
interfacing projects and much more.